<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[ 
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../common/global.ent">
 %globalents; 
 <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
 ]>
<chapter>
         
         
                    <title>Management Model</title>
         
                    <abstract>&abstract-management;</abstract>

          <section id="mng_setup_process">
                    <title>Setup Process</title>
                    <para>The management of any project begins with the process of setting up that particular project. With this in mind, we start the
                              &productname;. Cookbook Management Module with the procedures outlining how to begin the application process. The rest
                              of this section will describe the process of how a school goes about applying for a &productname;.</para>                    
                    <section id="mng_info">
                              <title>Obtaining Information About the Programme</title>
                              <para>There are many ways to obtain information about the &productname; project. The following list presents the main
                                        was of doing so:</para>
                              <orderedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Word-of-Mouth</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>Traditionally, word-of-mouth has been the chief mechanism behind &productname;s'
                                                            popularity. Schools in similar districts are in contact with each other, principals create
                                                            forums, parents have communal relationships outside of their schools and the learners
                                                            themselves have informal friendship circles. A school with a computer centre, especially
                                                            if it is still quite new, is quick to advertise their ownership.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">The Press</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>The Shuttleworth Foundation makes periodic press releases advertising their projects and
                                                            programmes to the community at large. &productname;s often advertise large install
                                                            events or sponsored schools in the programme.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">The &productname; Website</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>The web portal <ulink url="http://www.tuxlab.org.za">www.tuxlab.org.za</ulink> is the primary
                                                            source of information for the programme and is the home of all current information that is
                                                            &productname; related.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Help-Desk</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>The &productname; help-desk offers telephonic and e-mail support and can answer, or
                                                            redirect, all queries for the &productname; programme. Additionally, the project
                                                            administrator can be contacted telephonically or via e-mail.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Mailing List</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>The creation of a Linux User Group (LUG) centred around the activities in schools can host
                                                            various mailing lists pertaining to &productname;s, e.g. announce and chat. Interested
                                                            parties can register on these lists and receive information from volunteers and
                                                            &productname; team members directly.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                              </orderedlist>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_applying">
                              <title>Applying for a &productname;</title>
                              <para>When applying for your &productname; you will need to follow these steps:</para>
                              <procedure>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Read Documentation</title>
                                                  <para>As a starting point, you need to read the Introduction section of the &productname;
                                                            Cookbook. If possible please read through the rest of the Cookbook and the documents
                                                            contained in the Appendix.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Return the Questionnaire</title>
                                                  <para>The “School Awareness Questionnaire” (see Appendix E) needs to be filled out and returned to the
                                                            &productname; project coordinator. This is used for the &productname; team to
                                                            perform an initial assessment on the applicant and to gain various details on the school,
                                                            e.g. contacts, size &amp; demographics.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Complete the Business Plan</title>
                                                  <para>The Business Plan needs to be completed and returned to the &productname; project
                                                            coordinator. There is a “Business Plan Guidelines” in Appendix A to use as a
                                                            starting point for you to understand what is needed in the business plan.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Attend an Installation</title>
                                                  <para>It is ordinarily required that the applying school sends a representative to a
                                                            &productname; install at another school. The obvious exception being if
                                                            &productname;s enters into a new geographic area. The representative must sign the
                                                            attendance register which will be sent back to the &productname; office by the
                                                            installing school.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>School Visit</title>
                                                  <para>The &productname; team will physically visit the school at this stage. The reason for this
                                                            is to:</para>
                                                  <itemizedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>initiate personal contact</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>visually assess the school</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>check that the requirements have been met</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </itemizedlist>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Attend Another Installation</title>
                                                  <para>The &productname; team will notify the applicant that they are being processed further and
                                                            that should attend another installation. If the school has already attended other
                                                            installations then this step is waived, as is often the case.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Confirm</title>
                                                  <para>The &productname; team will then send a letter of confirmation to the school and will set
                                                            up a date for the &productname; installation.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>School Infrastructure</title>
                                                  <para>On confirmation, the school must prepare their proposed venue before the installation date.
                                                            The <emphasis>Infrastructure</emphasis>, <emphasis>Hardware</emphasis>, and
                                                                      <emphasis>Software</emphasis> modules of the &productname; are available to
                                                            assist you in this preparation.</para>
                                        </step>
                                        <step>
                                                  <title>Second School Visit</title>
                                                  <para>The &productname; team will visit the school again before installation to ensure that the
                                                            room is ready and meets the requirements.</para>
                                        </step>
                              </procedure>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_selection">
                              <title>Selection Process</title>
                              <para>The selection process describes the criteria that the &productname; team considers when choosing schools for
                                        installation. It can be considered subjective in some areas, however, there is often no substitute for
                                        experience.</para>
                              <para>Core information about the school is obtained from the questionnaire, the business plan and any interview
                                        conducted during a school visit. If the schools is part of a programme run by another organisation then they
                                        will be consulted as well.</para>
                              <para>Schools are assessed not only on enthusiasm and commitment to the programme but also on their willingness and
                                        ability to contribute to its objectives.</para>
                              <section id="mng_questionnaire">
                                        <title>Questionnaire</title>
                                        <para>The information that the questionnaire should yield includes the following:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Does the school already have a computer lab?</para>
                                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>If so, then details on its size, usage and how it was obtained
                                                                           are important</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>How it is managed and incorporated is also important</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>What existing software is available and used</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                            </itemizedlist>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The same above applies to computers in the school that are not part of a computer
                                                                      lab, e.g. the secretary's workstation</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>What is the perceived level of computer literacy in the school</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>What is the Open Source level of awareness and literacy</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section id="mng_business_plan">
                                        <title>Business Plan</title>
                                        <para>The business plan should give an indication of:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>How the school intends to use the lab and who it will be for</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>How ready the school is for the physical infrastructure</para>
                                                            <orderedlist>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>In terms of location and budget</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>In terms of how the staff could be managed into a committee with
                                                                           a facilitator</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                            </orderedlist>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>If the school is aware of the risks and opportunities associated with having a
                                                                      computer lab</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>How the school intends to take ownership of the lab</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The schools' management level and history of success</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The schools' plan and vision for sustainability</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The schools' operational plan which should include a budget outlay for
                                                            maintenance</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>In general though, the schools often don't have any frame of reference regarding computer centres to be
                                                  able to supply completely relevant information. The questionnaire and business plan should highlight
                                                  this.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="mng_school_visit">
                                        <title>School Visit</title>
                                        <para>The school visit can be a very subjective process. A well run school is often characterised by clean
                                                  grounds, disciplined children and a visible level of respect. It is also possible to get a sense of
                                                  the principals' motivations behind applying for a &productname; at this stage by analysing the
                                                  type of queries they make. Occasionally it is very self evident that the prime motivation behind the
                                                  application is to obtain the infrastructure only. The visit will then largely centre around the
                                                  type, cost and power of the donated computer lab with very little attention drawn to any of the
                                                  softer issues.</para>
                                        <para>Visiting the school also affords the chance to verify the information submitted in the questionnaire and
                                                  the business plan. It has happened that a school has stored their existing equipment in a store-room
                                                  before applying for a &productname;.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="mng_selection_criteria">
                                        <title>Selection Criteria</title>
                                        <para>Choosing an appropriate schools is difficult at best if there are a lot of applicants. Generally though,
                                                  schools are chosen to build clusters geographically.</para>
                                        <section>
                                                  <title>Geographic Clustering</title>
                                                  <para>Each cluster contains a minimum of three schools.</para>
                                                  <para>The cluster model behind &productname;s is a very powerful way of fusing communities
                                                            together and encouraging support and collaboration. Strong clusters are thus desirable and
                                                            it is important to ensure that schools are clustered geographically close to each other to
                                                            reduce the transport burden on the facilitators for attending meetings and training
                                                            sessions.</para>
                                                  <para>Often, an installation cycle is centred around building up clusters that show promise and
                                                            enthusiasm but have large distances to cover for events.</para>
                                        </section>
                                        <section>
                                                  <title>Commitment</title>
                                                  <para>The application process requires that the applying school attend at least two installations at
                                                            other school. This is done in attempt to asses their “buy-in” to the programme.
                                                            Additionally, a school that attends installations, workshops, training and cluster
                                                            meetings, even when they do not have a computer centre, will definitely be considered with
                                                            more sincerity than those that have not shown a similar level of enthusiasm and commitment
                                                            to the programme.</para>
                                        </section>
                                        <section>
                                                  <title>Budget and Financial Backing</title>
                                                  <para>The selected school is expected to provide the physical infrastructure required for housing
                                                            the &productname;. The Letter of Intent and Criteria dictates what the school is
                                                            responsible for supplying and includes:</para>
                                                  <itemizedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>All electrical work</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>Network trunking</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>Desks, chairs and storage space</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>Adequate security</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>Insurance</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </itemizedlist>
                                                  <para>This implies an initial capital outlay from the school. The school must also be able to
                                                            support its' computer lab. Hardware has a limited warranty period and the Shuttleworth
                                                            Foundation only guarantees the refurbished computer equipment for a period of 3 months
                                                            after installation. The school therefore needs to be prepared for maintenance expenses
                                                            and, possibly in the future, upgrade expenses.</para>
                                        </section>
                                        <section>
                                                  <title>Resourced vs. Non-Resourced Schools</title>
                                                  <para>Schools in South Africa are often described as being resourced or non-resourced.
                                                            Alternatively, non-resourced schools are also referred to as disadvantaged and resourced
                                                            schools as ex-Model C schools.</para>
                                                  <para>Whatever the terminology, the Shuttleworth Foundation &productname; programme has focused
                                                            on schools that do not have the resources or the capacity to facilitate the creation of
                                                            their own computer lab. Although this is the focus, there have been exceptions where an
                                                            advantaged school has been provided with a &productname; because its' business plan
                                                            reflected its' plan to extend the &productname;'s influence and accessibility to the
                                                            greater community. Somerset College is such an example of a resourced school whose plans
                                                            where to help fund a &productname; for a neighbouring school, Macassar Primary, as
                                                            well as servicing their community. </para>
                                                  <para>Such variety is believed to be important as different perspectives and competence levels
                                                            within a cluster can prove to be constructive.</para>
                                        </section>
                                        <section>
                                                  <title>Primary vs. Secondary Institutions</title>
                                                  <para>The demographics of the &productname; programme have so far favoured primary schools for
                                                            the following reasons:</para>
                                                  <itemizedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>Primary schools are easier to provide for in terms of content and
                                                                           curriculum software</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>Consequently the demands on the power of the computing environment are
                                                                           less</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>The Khanya project in the Western Cape has focused more on providing
                                                                           computer centres in secondary schools. Primary schools did not have a
                                                                           similar project focused on their needs.</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </itemizedlist>
                                                  <para>The &productname; programme does include secondary schools though for the following
                                                            reasons:</para>
                                                  <orderedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>To provide a platform for developing a model that encompasses all aspects
                                                                           of basic education.</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>To provide a platform for piloting other Shuttleworth Foundation projects
                                                                           that require a computer facility</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </orderedlist>
                                        </section>
                                        <section>
                                                  <title>Exclusion</title>
                                                  <para>In light of the above, a school will only be denied it's application under the following
                                                            conditions:</para>
                                                  <itemizedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>It is guilty of misrepresentation in its application questionnaire and
                                                                           business plan</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>The facilitators do not attend other installations</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>The schools does not supply the required infrastructure</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>The school does not supply the required paperwork</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </itemizedlist>
                                                  <para>Generally though, the applicant will not be denied, as such, but rather not accepted. The
                                                            difference being that the applicant is not formally disqualified but rather given time to
                                                            qualify completely in the future.</para>
                                        </section>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_install_process">
                              <title>Installation Process</title>
                              <para>This installation process describes the events that happen on the day.</para>
                              <para>In the past, the installation process has evolved from performing as many activities as possible with all the
                                        roll-players to performing only relevant activities. An example would be that the server is no longer
                                        installed on-site at the school on installation day. The reason for this change is that the server
                                        installation is largely automatic and quite uninteresting for the participants.</para>
                              <para>The current &productname; install process involves the following activities:</para>
                              <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>The workstations are refurbished before the time and delivered on to the school on the
                                                            Thursday prior to a Saturday install.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>The installation date would have been announced to the volunteers on the mailing lists.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>On the install Saturday, the volunteers are rounded up and assigned rolls and responsibilities
                                                            for the day.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>On arrival at the school, the participants are given a crash course in networking. The network
                                                            cables are cut, crimped and laid in conduits by the school staff, learners and
                                                  volunteers.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>If necessary, the network cards will be installed into the workstations on the day.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>The switch and server are installed and connected to the workstations.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Monitors are adjusted and networks tested.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                              </itemizedlist>
                              <para>If time and resources allow, the following activities on the day can add value to the whole process and event:</para>
                              <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Some kind of software installation process can be shown to the participants.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Allow the participants to get inside a computer, either by opening some up or by letting them
                                                            install the network cards.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>A basic tutorial session on system administration and what the capabilities of the computer
                                                            lab are.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                              </itemizedlist>
                              <para>Basically, the more interactive and hands-on the event is, the more the participants gain from the experience.</para>
                              <para>The school is expected to have at least a 50% staff attendance at the installation. This is important as it helps
                                        to build ownership of the &productname; from within.</para>
                              <para>Finally, the attendance register is collected and the Memorandum of Understanding (MoU)(see Appendix F) is signed
                                        with the Principal. The MoU outlines the purpose of the donation and the expectations from all of the parties
                                        involved. It essentially covers the criteria laid down in the Letter of Intent and the various support
                                        documentation. The attendance register is used for the obvious purposes of tracking installation attendance
                                        for the application process.</para>
                    </section>
          </section>
          <section id="mng_change_management">
                    <title>Change Management</title>
                    <para>For a school with no previous exposure to ICTs, there are a few changes within the school management that might need to be
                              addressed. There are some preconditions that need to be established with the school as part of the application process.</para>
                    <section id="mng_buy_in">
                              <title>Executive Buy-In</title>
                              <para>The principal and the school governing body (SGB) needs to be aware of the issues obtaining a &productname;.
                                        An initial capital expenditure will be required from the school to build infrastructure. This will normally
                                        have to be authorised by the SGB. This executive also needs to be aware that funds need to be allocated for
                                        insurance of the lab and possible future upgrades or maintenance.</para>
                              <para>Support from the principal and SGB is very important to the ongoing success of the school's &productname;.
                                        Teachers will be more motivated knowing that a level of accountability is in place. Certain &productname;
                                        activities, like open-days, involve the outside community and it is essential that the school executive are
                                        involved in taking ownership of such events.</para>
                              <para>The principal is also ultimately responsible for assigning rolls and responsibilities within their staff around
                                        the management of the &productname;. &productname; facilitators and the computer committee need to be
                                        held accountable by the principal.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_computer_committee">
                              <title>Computer Committee</title>
                              <para>Each school is required to form a computer committee consisting of at least three members of staff. This committee
                                        will manage the day-to-day running of the laboratory as well as provide feedback reports to the Foundation.
                                        The committee is also expected to formalise new strategies for integrating the laboratory usage into the
                                        educational curriculum, create internal support and maintenance resources as well as employ or appoint a
                                        facilitator to provide training during school hours. The computer committee is also expected to promote open
                                        source software awareness to the entire school community and allow access to the centre after normal school
                                        hours. </para>
                              <para>The computer committee is ultimately the group that is responsible for the running of the &productname; and
                                        its inclusion into the schools operations. They are required to submit a timetable to the &productname;
                                        coordinator outlining how the &productname; is to be included in class times.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_clustering">
                              <title>Clustering</title>
                              <para>The schools are built into clusters during the selection process.</para>
                              <para>The support process hinges on the schools collaborating within their clusters to try and solve technical problems
                                        as well as share best practises around the use and integration of the &productname;s.</para>
                              <para>To ensure that there is communication between clustered schools, the representatives of the schools in each
                                        cluster are required to form a committee which includes at least two representatives from each school. These
                                        cluster committees meet at least once a quarter to share ideas, and experiences and discuss approaches to
                                        managing and utilising the &productname;.</para>
                              <para>In many cases the first level of support is best provided by a peer group member who has faced similar problems.
                                        Not only does this build a co-operation between schools but it also fosters the sharing of skills between
                                        administrators and learners. It also serves to remove (or break) the perceived barrier to technology skills:
                                        by helping one another, learners and teachers are not merely passive recipients of technology services but are
                                        playing an involved role in the process.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_servicing_community">
                              <title>Servicing the Community</title>
                              <para>The &productname;, although it belongs to the school, is intended to service the local community around the
                                        school as well. The school is encouraged to activate the parents, learners and community at large to engage in
                                        the use and future of the &productname; through participation, support and training.</para>
                              <para>Some specific activities include the following:</para>
                              <orderedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Open Days</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>The schools are encouraged (and incentivised) to hold community Open Days at least once a
                                                            month. The objective is to open the &productname; up to the greater community and help
                                                            to increase exposure to its capabilities and opportunities. Activities could include
                                                            holding short courses (e.g. basic word-processing etc.)</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Adult Literacy</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>Each school is urged to implement a programme that will allow community members to receive
                                                            computer training courses after normal school hours. This program can be implemented to
                                                            create funds for the salary of a facilitator or to cover the cost of maintenance of the
                                                            lab or further expansion the lab.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Open ICDL Training and Testing Centres</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>The Open ICDL is the official open source version of the internationally renowned
                                                            International Computers Driving Licence. It is a certification that covers computer use
                                                            centred around OpenOffice.org and connectivity.</para>
                                                  <para>To date, the &productname; programme has helped to established Windermere Primary as an
                                                            official testing and training centre for the OpenICDL. Schools are able to generate
                                                            funding through the offering of ICDL training courses to the community.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Internet Café</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>Those schools that have an internet connection to the &productname; are presented with an
                                                            opportunity to open a community internet café. The lab could be used after school hours
                                                            and the school could raise funds towards paying for the connection fee and for maintaining
                                                            the &productname;.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>
                                                            <emphasis role="bold">Computer Clubs</emphasis>
                                                  </para>
                                                  <para>Computer clubs within the schools offer a platform for learners, educators and the community
                                                            to share expertise, experiences and activities around the use of computers. Such clubs
                                                            should be the hub of the &productname; where members take ownership of the lab and its
                                                            future.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                              </orderedlist>
                    </section>
          </section>
          <section>
                    <title>Post Install Management</title>
                    <section id="mng_reporting">
                              <title>Reporting</title>
                              <para>To ensure the successful development and growth of the &productname; model, accurate and relevant feedback
                                        from the schools is essential. The schools are encouraged (and incentivised) to produce reports on its
                                        activities including:</para>
                              <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Quarterly reports on the general use of the &productname; within the school including:</para>
                                                  <itemizedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>how it has been incorporated into the school's timetable</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>what training is provided</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>what activities have been scheduled and held</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>a guideline for the report is available (see Appendix B)</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Curriculum aligned lesson plans, if available, should be submitted to the &productname;
                                                            coordinator</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Evaluation forms on training provided to the school should be returned to the
                                                            &productname; coordinator</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Activity reports on Open Days, after school training programmes and any event that utilises
                                                            the &productname; in a constructive way</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Attendance registers for meetings and workshops.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                              </itemizedlist>
                              <para>In essence, these reports help the &productname; coordinator to track the usage of the &productname;s in
                                        the schools.</para>
                              <para>The MoU actually makes such reporting a requirement. The guidelines are there for schools that are not sure how to
                                        construct the reports. The schools are welcome to submit them in whatever format they desire as long as the
                                        criteria are met for required information.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_training_management">
                              <title>Training</title>
                              <para>As part of the installation process, the &productname; team schedules initial whole school training shortly
                                        after the hardware is set up. This forms a total of 6 hours on-site training that covers some of the basic
                                        skills around using a &productname; workstation, from logging in to writing simple documents and
                                        spreadsheets.</para>
                              <para>Additional training needs to be managed by the training providers (usually partners to the &productname;
                                        programme, e.g. Computers 4 Kids), the school principal and the &productname; facilitator.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_incentive">
                              <title>Incentive Scheme</title>
                              <para>The incentive scheme is designed to encourage and reward the use of the correct (and required) procedures behind
                                        running a tuXlab. Points are assigned to a school for correct usage of the support process, regular reporting
                                        and hosting events and meetings. These points accumulate and can eventually be cashed in for printers, extra
                                        workstation or a host of other items. The scheme is outlined in the “tuXlab Incentive Scheme” document found
                                        both in the Appendix E and online at the <ulink url="http://www.tuxlab.org.za/files/incentives.pdf">TuXlab
                                                  Webportal</ulink>.</para>
                              <para>The incentive scheme servers two main purposes:</para>
                              <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>on the one hand it encourages schools to engage in the &productname; activities,
                                                  and</para>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>on the other hand it provides a mechanism and a framework for tracking of events and reports
                                                            from the schools.</para>
                                        </listitem>
                              </itemizedlist>
                              <para>The various rewards available are all chosen for relevance to a computer centre, e.g. printers, extra workstations
                                        and additional training.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_budget">
                              <title>Budget</title>
                              <para>As with every education and business project there has to be a <emphasis role="bold">budget</emphasis>. This makes
                                        sense when you think of what installing and running a &productname; entails.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Capital Expenditure</title>
                                        <para>The &productname; model works on the thin-client model using refurbished computers and open source
                                                  software. As such it is an extremely cost effective solution.</para>
                                        <para>Traditionally, the school has been responsible for providing the physical infrastructure for the venue.
                                                  This includes, as mentioned above, the security, desktops and electrical work.</para>
                                        <para>The actual computer hardware is then paid for by a donor. The server and switch are procured new so that
                                                  a decent hardware warranty is in place. The workstations are refurbished machines and are easy to
                                                  replace should they fail.</para>
                                        <para>Currently, at the middle of 2006, the cost breakdown for a &productname; is as follows:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Xeon Server: R14200</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>24 Port Switch: R950</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Power Cables x 20: R500</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Network Cards/Boot PROMs x 20: R1700</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Network cabling, boots and jacks: R500</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>tuXlab Starter Kit: R200</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                      <emphasis role="bold">Total: R18050</emphasis>
                                                            </para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>The initial training that the school receives can be broken into 6 hours at R50/hour yielding R300 per
                                                  school. Additional costs contributing to the total cost of a tuXlab would include staff costs of the
                                                  tuXlab team, the running of a support desk and other external activities.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="mng_lab_sustainability">
                                        <title>Sustainability</title>
                                        <para>The SGB needs to be aware that there are running costs with regards to maintaining a working computer
                                                  lab. Some of the items include:</para>
                                        <orderedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>making provision for a computer facilitator</para>
                                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>can be a staff member</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>or external to the school</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                            </itemizedlist>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>hardware maintenance</para>
                                                            <itemizedlist>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>the school needs to ensure that maintenance options are
                                                                           available for the</para>
                                                                           <para>server and switch past their distributor warranty</para>
                                                                           <para>workstations past their 3 month tuXlab warranty</para>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                                      <listitem>
                                                                           <para>maintenance options including:</para>
                                                                           <itemizedlist>
                                                                           <listitem>
                                                                           <para>employing a service provider to maintain the
                                                                           equipment</para>
                                                                           </listitem>
                                                                           <listitem>
                                                                           <para>entering a lease agreement with a computer
                                                                           financial services organisation (e.g.
                                                                           RentWorks)</para>
                                                                           </listitem>
                                                                           <listitem>
                                                                           <para>sourcing maintenance or refurbished
                                                                           workstations through a local
                                                                           refurbishment house (e.g.
                                                                           FreeCom)</para>
                                                                           </listitem>
                                                                           </itemizedlist>
                                                                      </listitem>
                                                            </itemizedlist>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </orderedlist>
                                        <para>Further budgetary considerations include additional training for the staff, sending facilitators on
                                                  workshops or courses and purchasing peripheral equipment to help in class delivery (e.g. data
                                                  projectors).</para>
                                        <para>Hidden costs could include electricity, transport to training sessions, paper and printer toner.
                                                  Internet connectivity is another area that a school should consider in its budget.</para>
                                        <para>Please read the Sustainability Module that is also part of the &productname; Cookbook.</para>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section id="mng_project_support">
                              <title>Programme Support</title>
                              <para>You do not need to be alone when considering or utilising a &productname;. Support for you and for your
                                        &productname; programme is available from various sources. We discuss two of these sources here:</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Department of Education</title>
                                        <para>The educational sector is a difficult ground to operate in. The level of ICT competence in
                                                  under-privileged communities is quite low and educators are challenged enough with current tasks to
                                                  engage in furthering their computer skills.</para>
                                        <para>The support of the Department of Education (DoE) is thus essential. A well placed letter can literally
                                                  make a world of difference. For example, if attendance for a workshop at a school is critical to the
                                                  success of a certain programme, then a letter of support from a DoE head can ensure that full
                                                  attendance is attained. DoE buy-in to the programme lends it credibility.</para>
                                        <para>Similarly, software, content and applications that carry a stamp of approval from the curriculum
                                                  development department are more likely to be engaged by the teachers than those that aren't. If a
                                                  software programme targets specific learning areas and outcomes that the DoE has identified, then
                                                  the educators' task becomes a lot clearer.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="mng_partnerships">
                                        <title>Partnerships</title>
                                        <para>Partnerships can include content providers, trainers, donors, sponsors or even various levels of
                                                  consulting. The &productname; definition of a partners is one in which a 3rd party supports the
                                                  &productname; programme to the extent that products or services are granted either for free or
                                                  for a reduced cost to the beneficiaries.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>An example would be Edupac whose school management application is to released under
                                                                      an open source licence and made freely available. Additionally, Edupac agreed to
                                                                      install, train and support their product in as many &productname; schools as
                                                                      existed at no cost. The sustainable future would see a basic reduced support
                                                                      cost model for the schools.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Another example is Computers 4 Kids. Their DoE approved software was ported to the
                                                                      linux operating system and provided free of charge to all &productname;s.
                                                                      Although not technically an open source product, the partnership is a good
                                                                      example of a collaborative relationship with a proprietary software provider
                                                                      that makes their product available at no cost for the programme. Additionally
                                                                      they provide training and support to the schools at no cost.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Other examples include:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>telecommunications service providers reducing their rates for public schools</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>content developers releasing their material under an open licence</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>large corporation donating equipment and providing media exposure</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>the media themselves keeping track of the programme</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>All these examples are partnerships that aid the beneficiaries of &productname;s directly.</para>
                                        <para>Some guidelines should be kept in mind when dealing with social enterprises though:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>There are organisations looking only for mileage out of the t&productname;
                                                                      programme and not fronting anything tangible. They generally are aiming for a
                                                                      “&productname; Partner” logo by providing a product or service that does not
                                                                      honour the open spirit of the community or the programme. Generally such
                                                                      organisations are looking for the &productname; team to coordinate a
                                                                      targeted marketing strategy for them. Such organisations are generally dealt
                                                                      with by explaining that they are welcome to approach schools directly.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Other partner organisations might not have the capacity to provide a social
                                                                      enterprise offering. The expectation is often there for the &productname;
                                                                      team to produce the service for them in, for example, installing their software
                                                                      or supporting their product. This is not always feasible and the caveat should
                                                                      be there when drafting a partnership agreement.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>In drafting a partnership agreement, it should be kept clear and concise what roles,
                                                                      responsibilities and activities lie with which parties. In light of the above,
                                                                      partner organisations can have a tendency to expect the &productname; team
                                                                      to manage and operationalise their activities for them because of the cost
                                                                      sacrifice they might be making.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Accurate reporting from partners should be maintained. It is important to receive
                                                                      feedback from all aspects of the programme, especially around areas of support.
                                                                      A partners support desk should integrate into the &productname; support
                                                                      desk, at the very least on a communicative level.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>With respect to reporting, where applicable the &productname;s support desk
                                                                      should be preserved. In other words, a partner organisation should preferably
                                                                      integrate their help desk with &productname;s in such a manner that both
                                                                      operations know where to dispatch support tickets and can track problems
                                                                      accordingly.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                    </section>
          </section>
</chapter>
