<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[ 
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../common/global.ent">
 %globalents; 
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<chapter>
          
                    <title>Introduction</title>
                    <abstract>&abstract-introduction;</abstract>
          
          <section id="introduction">
                    <title>Overview</title>
                    <para>For those reading this book who have never heard of a &productname; or who have heard of about the &productname;
                              project but are unsure of what it entails, we have provided this overview. Just like a satellite image of a town
                              provides general detail about the layout and location of buildings and streets but cannot show you the street signs or
                              the people walking along the roads, so this overview provides only a general understanding of the project as a whole.
                              You will need to read each of the sections of the &productname; cookbook AND work with a &productname; project
                              before you are fully aware of all the details.</para>
                    <section>
                              <title>Motivation</title>
                              <para>There are many motivating factors for the initiation and perpetuation of the &productname; project. There are
                                        economical, social, and personal reason's involved. One of the basic motivating factor's regarding the
                                        &productname; project is the lower costs involved in creating and maintaining a &productname;. The
                                        software that is used is Free and Open Sourced Software, able to be freely distributed and modified. The
                                        hardware used in a &productname; can also be donated second had computers, further reducing the costs of
                                        the &productname; and encouraging the cooperation and involvement of local businesses and partnerships.</para>
                              <para>The &productname; project involves the whole school community. The teachers have to know how to set up and
                                        install the system, and are empowered through these skills to teach what they have learned to others. The
                                        students who use the &productname; have their own local email addresses and profiles, establishing their
                                        ownership of the &productname; project. Both the teachers and the students can look at the programming
                                        code that creates the applications that they use and learn how to produce and improve it.</para>
                              <para>All of the above reasons allow us to say that the &productname; project is motivated by community need.
                                        Primarily the need for improved education, but also the need for community upliftment and community ownership.
                                        These community based needs are not only present in South Africa, but are present in many other countries in
                                        Africa and around the world.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                              <title>Background</title>
                              <para>The &productname; project has its roots in the vision of the Shuttleworth Foundation and in the Foundation's
                                        commitment to improve the standard of education in South Africa. This is a huge task with many facets, and
                                        just putting computers in schools is not nearly enough. The one critical factor in education is the people
                                        involved: the teachers and the learners they have to educate. For computer labs to make a difference, the
                                        people who use them must understand them and be able to use them for anything that they can imagine. They must
                                        be able to take ownership of the computers and the software that they run, and to create new learning material
                                        to share with each other and with society as a whole.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Open Source Learning Centres Background</title>
                                        <para>In 2002 the Shuttleworth Foundation started to actively promote the use open source software as a
                                                  computer lab solution for schools. The Foundation funded several projects to establish open source
                                                  based computer labs in schools, as well as an internally initiating a pilot to prove the
                                                  effectiveness of open source software as a school computing solution. The Foundation also initiated
                                                  a project to facilitate the involvement of volunteers in refurbishing computers and establishing
                                                  open source learning centres.</para>
                                        <para>Based on the success of the pilot and volunteer project, the Foundation extended the pilot to establish
                                                  a further 80 open source learning centres in the Western Cape. This goal was reached in November
                                                  2004.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="intr_shuttleworth-tuxlab-program-outline">
                                        <title>Original Shuttleworth &productname; Program Outline</title>
                                        <para>Under the guidance of the Shuttleworth Foundation, both primary and secondary schools were involved. In
                                                  order to maximise the impact of the program, schools were (and still are) selected in clusters.
                                                  Through clustering, schools are able to plan the use of the centres together, and they can share
                                                  resources and community support. We believe that clustering is the best method of ensuring that
                                                  schools remain self-sufficient in terms of support in the future. This is supported by the
                                                            <emphasis>Computers in Schools</emphasis> survey of 2000, which states (my emphasis):</para>
                                        <blockquote>
                                                  <attribution>
                                                            <ulink url="http://www.school.za/research/uwc-epu/screen/Executive%20Summary.pdf">
                                                                      Computers in Schools, 2000</ulink>
                                                  </attribution>
                                                  <para>Experiences from other countries, whatever their stage of development, show that factors which
                                                            accompany the successful implementation of ICTs in schools are <emphasis>networks of
                                                                      connectivity</emphasis> and <emphasis>structured and continuous
                                                            programmes</emphasis> to train teachers to use the new technology for educational
                                                            purposes.</para>
                                        </blockquote>
                                        <para>Within a cluster, schools are selected based on criteria originally set by the Foundation. At a very
                                                  minimum, these criteria include the availability of a secure computing environment, guaranteed
                                                  commitment of the school (including governing body) to the project, as well as proof of
                                                  comprehensive plans to introduce the &productname; into school activities. Additional criteria
                                                  could be set for each cluster, depending on the needs of that community.</para>
                                        <para>In 2005, hundreds of &productname;s were installed throughout South Africa in partnership with local
                                                  organisations and user groups. The project was also launched in Namibia, and reports of roll-outs
                                                  overseas (such as a large-scale project in Azerbaijan! ) have also been communicated.</para>
                                        <para>The &productname; programme is now a fully fledged organisation. From it's beginnings in the
                                                  Shuttleworth Foundation it is becoming a self organising, self sustaining entity that continues to
                                                  bring quality information technology and infrastructure to the education system.</para>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                              <title>Objectives</title>
                              <para>While an understanding of computers and information technology is critical in our modern global society, they are
                                        not a sufficient goal in themselves. There are many other fields of knowledge that beckon to be explored, and
                                        to be discussed and debated with other people. However, publishing and distributing books on paper is
                                        expensive, and unless you are in a big city with the means to travel around easily, it is awkward and costly
                                        to take part in the global conversation. Information technology offers us a chance to leapfrog these problems
                                        by providing access to vast resources of texts, curricula, art and music via the internet, and allows us to
                                        stay in touch by electronic means, even in remote areas.</para>
                              <para>Without some degree of mastery of technology it is easy to miss the debates of real importance on the internet. To
                                        understand legislation concerning intellectual property, access to information and privacy issues, it is
                                        crucial to understand what the technology offers and how it differs from the possibilities of the past. In a
                                        sense, this is the real meaning of the digital divide: if you don't understand how computers and networks can
                                        be used, you can starve even in the midst of plenty of conversation and information.</para>
                              <para>To accomplish these objectives of social innovation and empowerment, and to further the uptake of technology in
                                        South Africa, the Shuttleworth Foundation launched the &productname; project. The objective of this
                                        project is to establish a national network of computer laboratories based exclusively on open source software.
                                        The &productname; project strongly believes that open source software should be the preferred choice of
                                        software for schooling in South Africa. Open source software provides users with freedoms not obtainable from
                                        proprietary software. This includes the freedom to obtain, use, modify and distribute the software.</para>
                              <para>Great, so now that we know what we have, the question is: "What can we do with it?" We can see communities using
                                        the &productname; project to do three things:</para>
                              <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="../images/ditaldivide.png"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                              </mediaobject>
                              <itemizedlist>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Begin to <emphasis role="bold">bridging the Digital Divide</emphasis>.</para>
                                                  <para>A &productname; can provide access to information, books, music, news, and myriads of
                                                            other resources. It can also provide new ways to communicate with your peers, near and
                                                            far, and open channels of communication to organisations that may be hard to reach because
                                                            they are far away or widely distributed.</para>

                                                  <para>In order to manage this, we must build something sustainable, unbreakable and flexible.
                                                            Instead of leaping ahead, for example by accepting an expensive lab that we cannot
                                                            maintain, with proprietary software that we cannot study, we must build steadily from the
                                                            ground up, so that we have a foundation that will last. To do this, we have to keep some
                                                            things in mind:</para>
                                                  <itemizedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>The components of the &productname; must be as cheap as possible. We
                                                                           must make use of what is available, and make the parts generic and
                                                                           interchangeable. We must also use standards, for example
                                                                           <acronym>TCP/IP</acronym> - for networking. </para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>The &productname; shouldn't require a permanent internet connection in
                                                                           order to access cultural goods, and enable participation in the
                                                                           culture.</para>
                                                                      <para>Especially in South Africa, a high-bandwidth internet connection is
                                                                           incredibly expensive. Wireless service providers are just starting to
                                                                           appear in the big urban centres, but even they cost hundreds of Rands
                                                                           per month, and that's for home users.</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </itemizedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>In this way, we <emphasis role="bold">foster self-reliance and create local expertise, while
                                                                      building an international community</emphasis>.</para>
                                                  <para>In one of his essays, Richard Stallman writes about the importance of free software in
                                                            developing local IT expertise:</para>
                                                  <blockquote>
                                                            <attribution>Richard Stallman, <ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/schools.html">
                                                                           http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/schools.html</ulink></attribution>
                                                            <para>Free software permits students to learn how software works. When students reach
                                                                      their teens, some of them want to learn everything there is to know about their
                                                                      computer system and its software. That is the age when people who will be good
                                                                      programmers should learn it. To learn to write software well, students need to
                                                                      read a lot of code and write a lot of code. They need to read and understand
                                                                      real programs that people really use. They will be intensely curious to read the
                                                                      source code of the programs that they use every day.</para>
                                                  </blockquote>
                                        </listitem>
                                        <listitem>
                                                  <para>Lastly, we can also <emphasis role="bold">save money</emphasis>.</para>
                                                  <para>While it's essential to spend money on education, we have to make sure that the money goes as
                                                            far as possible. By using only free software in &productname;s, you save money in a
                                                            couple of ways:</para>
                                                  <orderedlist>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>There are no software license fees to be paid. The Linux operating system
                                                                           is world wide, stable, and FREE.</para>
                                                                      <para>In addition, for every Windows software product we have included a Linux
                                                                           alternative that looks for all intents the same. For example, a word
                                                                           processor (that can read Microsoft word document files, incidentally),
                                                                           a spreadsheet, a publisher, an HTML editor for creating web pages, a
                                                                           typing tutorial, etc. <footnote>
                                                                           <para>This paragraph is from <ulink
                                                                           url="http://wizzy.org.za/article/articleview/4/1/3"
                                                                           />.</para>
                                                                           </footnote></para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                            <listitem>
                                                                      <para>By using free software and open file formats that you can read without
                                                                           needing expensive software, we save money for the community.</para>
                                                                      <para>Whether they intend to or not, teachers make their learners' families buy
                                                                           proprietary software if they use it at school. By using free software
                                                                           that learners can take home, the school helps the community to save
                                                                           money.</para>
                                                            </listitem>
                                                  </orderedlist>
                                        </listitem>
                              </itemizedlist>
                    </section>
          </section>
          <section id="intr_tux_components">
                    <title>Lab Overview</title>
                    <section>
                              <title>&productname; Components</title>
                              <para>Maybe you've just taken acceptance of a brand new &productname;, or perhaps you're just dreaming about when it
                                        will all be done. Whatever the case may be, let's take a walk through the completed lab to see how everything
                                        fits together.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Lab Room</title>
                                        <para>Every &productname; consists of a room where people may come to use the facilities of the lab.</para>
                                        <para>The room is secured with a gate and burglar bars on the windows, and the really expensive components of
                                                  the &productname; are locked away even further, in another room or in a cage. </para>
                                        <para>The room provides a comfortable space to work in, with desks at the right height for the learners at the
                                                  school, and with enough plugs and cables for all the computers. All the users of the
                                                  &productname; may sit down at any of the workstations and log in, to find their working
                                                  environment just as they left it, even if they u logged in on a different computer.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Computers</title>
                                        <para>A &productname; usually contains between 20 and 25 workstation computers, although you may add more
                                                  workstations if you already have some computers, or if you can get donations. These workstations are
                                                  connected to a server computer by way of a high-speed network.</para>
                                        <para>The workstations are where the rubber hits the road, so to speak. They are standing out there on the
                                                  desks, and everyone who uses the &productname; is constantly using their keyboards and adjusting
                                                  their screens, and so they do undergo some wear and tear. Because they are intended to be accessible
                                                  to use, they are not that easy to secure. If something is locked away, it's hard to learn how to use
                                                  it. To deal with this state of affairs, &productname;s are designed so as to make the
                                                  workstations as cheap and as easy as possible to replace. They should be completely interchangeable,
                                                  and they store nothing: no documents, and no information about any user.</para>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                                  <imageobject>
                                                            <imagedata fileref="../images/workstation.png"/>
                                                  </imageobject>
                                                  <caption>A classroom workstation</caption>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                        <para>The server actually does all the work in a &productname;. If the server goes away, the workstations
                                                  will just stand around scratching their heads, like bees doing nothing when something happens to the
                                                  queen bee. Whatever you see when working at a &productname; workstation has been sent to the
                                                  workstation by the server over the network. All the documents you save, and all the information
                                                  regarding users, everything is stored on the server.</para>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                                  <imageobject>
                                                            <imagedata fileref="../images/server.png"/>
                                                  </imageobject>
                                                  <caption>A classroom server for a TuXlab,</caption>
                                        </mediaobject>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Software</title>
                                        <para>The software falls roughly into two categories: the operating system software, and applications. All the
                                                  computers in the lab run the Linux operating system (the workstations fetch their copy from the
                                                  server upon startup). This enables the server to display the applications it is running for all the
                                                  workstations on the screens of the workstations themselves, using the <application>X
                                                  Windows</application> system, the graphical windowing environment used by Linux.</para>
                                        <para>The applications installed in a &productname; are focused on an educational environment, and include
                                                  software that is essential for general computer literacy such as word processors, spreadsheet and
                                                  web browsers, as well as educational software that allow learners to practise skills (e.g. typing,
                                                  arithmetic) and knowledge (e.g. spelling, geography). Besides these, a &productname; contains a
                                                  great variety of programming languages, tools, texts and examples that can be used to teach
                                                  programming and to study how existing programs work, all the way from first principles to systems
                                                  architecture. Nothing is proprietary: you may examine the source code of every component in the
                                                  system.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Network</title>
                                        <para>The final critical component of a &productname; is the computer network that connects all the
                                                  machines in the room. If you're looking at a finished &productname;, the network cabling
                                                  shouldn't be terribly obvious. However, every workstation has a Ethernet cable plugged into it, and
                                                  you should be able to see the switch cabinet where all the cables go. However, if you were to look
                                                  inside the trunking running along the walls or under the desks, you would see that there is an
                                                  Ethernet cable for each and every workstation, connecting it to the network switch. The
                                                  &productname; server is also connected to the switch by a fly-lead (don't worry if these words
                                                  don't mean much to you yet... as you read through the infrastructure and hardware sections you will
                                                  gain a better understanding of what we are talking about).</para>
                                        <para>In this configuration, it is as if every workstation in the &productname; is connected directly to
                                                  the server. The switch itself is transparent to the network. It sees to it that network traffic from
                                                  the server is sent as directly as possible to the workstation for which it is intended. From the
                                                  perspective of the computers, it looks as though they're all connected directly to each other.</para>
                                        <para>The role of the server in the network is key to the functioning of a &productname;. The server is
                                                  the centre of &productname; environment. It may be easier to think of the server as a powerful
                                                  computer that is able to split itself up into many smaller, virtual computers. As a workstation
                                                  computer is switched on it first communicates with the server computer. The server creates an
                                                  individual space within itself that it identifies as that workstation. The workstation provides the
                                                  screen, the mouse, and the keyboard, but all the applications, memory usage, and disk space are part
                                                  of the server. All that the workstation has to do is take whatever has been typed or clicked and
                                                  communicate this through the network to the server, and then display whatever response the server
                                                  makes using that input.</para>
                                        <para>If anything goes amiss in a &productname;, there's a pretty good chance that it may be a problem
                                                  with the network, since (from the workstation's point of view) a broken network is just as bad as a
                                                  broken server. It can't do anything in either case.</para>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                              <title>Operating Software</title>
                              <para>There are many different distributions <xref linkend="intr_what-is-a-distribution"/> of Linux that can run the
                                        &productname; system. The following four distributions are specifically made for educational purposes and
                                        are the most likely to be installed with a &productname; environment.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Edubuntu</title>
                                        <para>Edubuntu is a Linux distribution designed for use in schools and classrooms. It is a branch of the
                                                  Ubuntu Linux project, also begun by the Shuttleworth Foundation. Included with Edubuntu is the Linux
                                                  Terminal Server Project, a large number of educational applications, including GCompris (educational
                                                  software for children aged 2 - 10), the KDE Edutainment Project (Language, Math, Science) and
                                                  Schooltool Calander.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Openlab/Openlab4</title>
                                        <para>OpenLab GNU/Linux is the oldest African developed GNU/Linux distribution. Started in 2001, the product
                                                  has built up a well deserved reputation for ease-of-use, innovation and user-oriented design.</para>
                                        <para>The latest stable version (4.0 - Perdita), was released in September of 2005. It comes with the new
                                                  installable LIVEcd, greatly improved OLAD (OpenLab ADministration tool) and many other innovations
                                                  ranging from back-end systems such as the hyperdrive suite which completely de-complex-ifies the
                                                  handling of removable media to user-level enhancements such as the highly integrated desktop theme
                                                  featuring the award winning Nuvola icon set.</para>
                                        <para>OpenLab GNU/Linux was initially developed as a niche solution for the education sector, but over its
                                                  four-year life-cycle, OpenLab has grown into a complete desktop operating system. OpenLab is well
                                                  suited for the home desktop, small business and many other environments, where it usually leaves
                                                  other contenders far behind. Developed using principles from extreme programming, with constant
                                                  involvement of a wide-range of participants in the process with frequent re-evalutation of designs,
                                                  OpenLab is an innovative, vibrant and above all fun platform.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>K-12</title>
                                        <para>
                                                  <ulink url="http://k12ltsp.org/contents.html"> K12LTSP</ulink> is based on the RedHat Fedora
                                                  distribution of Linux and the work of the <acronym>LTSP</acronym>. It's easy to install and
                                                  configure. It's distributed under the GNU General Public License. That means it's free and it's
                                                  based on Open Source software. It was started in the USA and now has <emphasis>Creative
                                                  Commons</emphasis> Courses and Text books. The K-12 project involves the Linux distribution, a
                                                  community forum, and a development community around the world. Software bundled with K12LTSP
                                                  includes web browsers, email, calender, contact managers, OpenOffice, Gimp, AbiWord, file sharing
                                                  with Windows and Macintosh networks, and auto configuration of many PCI based sound cards and
                                                  network adopters.</para>
                                        <para>This is quite a mouthful, so I'll unpack the terms one by one.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The <emphasis>
                                                                           <acronym>LTSP</acronym>
                                                                      </emphasis> is the Linux Terminal Server Project. This project assembles all the
                                                                      software components that are necessary for a computer to act as a fat server for
                                                                      a network of thin clients, and provides the configuration necessary for the
                                                                      server to function as such.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>RedHat Fedora Linux is the free distribution packaged by RedHat, Inc. The K12LTSP
                                                                      team has added an option to the RedHat installation menu, so that installing a
                                                                      classroom server is as simple as choosing the first installation option and
                                                                      answering some questions.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>The K12LTSP distribution tries to make it as easy as possible for you. It is a regular Fedora distro
                                                  with an option to install <acronym>LTSP</acronym> right there in the setup screen. When installing,
                                                  the <acronym>LTSP</acronym> option is the first item on the menu, added above the default
                                                  Workstation, Server and Custom options. This means that you don't have to mess around with the
                                                  configuration files until you've had a chance to see what it is they do, and by then you'll probably
                                                  only need to tweak them a little.</para>
                                        <para>The <acronym>LTSP</acronym> server defaults to an IP gateway and firewall when two Ethernet cards are
                                                  present. This will only be the case in &productname;s that are permanently online, which will
                                                  usually not be the case. Normally, the Wizzy server will be the gateway, as all &productname;s
                                                  with internet access use a Wizzy server.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Skolelinux</title>
                                        <para>Skolelinux is a free software project started in Norway. It's name is derived from the Norwegian 'Skole'
                                                  which means School. Skolelinux offers four different installation options on their installation CD
                                                  that will easily install a pre-configured educational network including main server, work stations
                                                  and thin client server.</para>
                              </section>
                    </section>
          </section>
          <section id="intr_software_concepts">
                    <title>Software Concepts</title>
                    <para>This section serves as an introduction to many of the concepts regarding computer software. We will examine what the
                              definition of an Operating System (OS) is, the concept of Linux, the definition of what a Linux distribution is, and
                              finally we will examine the world of open source software.</para>
                    <section id="intr_what-is-an-operating-system">
                              <title>What is an Operating System?</title>
                              <para>In the earliest days of computers, a whole machine was built to do only one thing, for example numerical
                                        integration. There was no clean distinction between hardware and software, as aspects of the program might be
                                        reflected by physical switches and jumpers set on the machine itself.</para>
                              <para>As computers became more general, the same computer could be programmed to do many different things. All these
                                        programs, however, would still have to deal with the hardware aspects of the machine, writing to the printer,
                                        reading from the magnetic drum memory, and so on. Since these jobs needed to be done over and over and over
                                        again, the bits of code that dealt with them could be shared among all the programs that run on that computer.
                                        This shared code, the code that handles the basic tasks any program needs in order to run, was the beginning
                                        of operating systems.</para>
                              <para>Today's operating systems are complex, sophisticated systems, that can schedule many different programs to run at
                                        once, and that provide such a comprehensive range of services that many programs can be compiled to run on
                                        many different operating systems, regardless of the variations in the underlying hardware.</para>
                              <para>An operating system ( <acronym>OS</acronym> for short) is the most basic layer of the software, and if your
                                        computer is switched on, the operating system kernel is the one program that will always be running. It
                                        provides a framework for all the subsystems that make up the computer.</para>
                              <para>Imagine, for a moment, that a computer is like a ship. The physical hardware is the steel or wooden hull that
                                        floats. The operating system is like the officers of a ship, and its subsystems are like the captain, the
                                        first mate, the engineer, the cook, and so on. They see to it that the engine is running and that the ship is
                                        on an even keel.</para>
                              <para>All the other software applications that run on the computer are like the rest of the crew and the passengers. The
                                        operating system manages the resources of the computer like the captain manages the crew of the ship. He
                                        maintains discipline, sees to it that the crew don't fall all over one another, do things in an orderly
                                        fashion, and keep everything shipshape.</para>
                              <para>If a program does something wrong, such as writing to memory that the operating system is using for something else
                                        (in the ship example, this is like making a hole in the hull!), the operating system lets the offending
                                        program know, shutting it down completely if necessary (it gets thrown in the brig!).</para>
                              <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="../images/operatingsystem1.gif"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                              </mediaobject>
                              <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="../images/operatingsystem2.gif"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                              </mediaobject>
                              <section id="intr_what-is-linux">
                                        <title>What is <emphasis>Linux</emphasis>?</title>
                                        <para>Linux is an <emphasis>operating system</emphasis> consisting of a central<emphasis>kernel</emphasis> as
                                                  well as all the hundreds of libraries, tools and utilities that make it usable as a computing
                                                  environment. The kernel was developed by Linus Torvalds, using the tools and utilities of the <ulink
                                                            url="http://www.gnu.org"> GNU project</ulink>. Together, the whole system is called
                                                  GNU/Linux. Some other common operating systems are the Unix family (including members like Linux,
                                                  BSD, AIX, Solaris, HP-UX, and others); DOS; Microsoft Windows; Amiga; and Mac <acronym>OS</acronym>.
                                                  An upcoming variety of operating systems, such as Symbian and PalmOS, run on cellphones. There are
                                                  special-purpose operating systems wherever you look, far more than you would have suspected.</para>
                                        <para>Linux is Free Software. So, not only is it OK to make copies of Linux and give them to your friends,
                                                  it's also fine to fix things while you're at it --- as long as you also freely provide your modified
                                                  source code to everyone else. When you're doing this, you're not just providing a freebie to the
                                                  people who get your fixes: you're also exercising your right to influence Linux, and to change the
                                                  way that you want it to work. In return for this right which has been granted to you, you must allow
                                                  those who come after you the same freedom in making use of your work. The issue is <ulink
                                                            url="http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">
                                                            <emphasis>freedom</emphasis>, not price</ulink>.</para>
                                        <note>
                                                  <title>Charging for Free Software</title>
                                                  <para>How can people build businesses on software if everything must be given away? Actually, you're
                                                            welcome to ask money, but then people are paying for your expertise and services, e.g.
                                                            assurances of support that you may give them. You may also provide added value, such as
                                                            attractive packaging and shipping. Only the source code itself must be available at
                                                            nominal cost.</para>
                                        </note>
                                        <para>No one company or individual "owns" Linux. It was developed, and is still being improved, by thousands
                                                  of programmers all over the world. Some are supported by businesses that make money from their work,
                                                  and some are volunteers who like to help people. Some are scientists who need computers to get their
                                                  work done, and who find it convenient to use Linux because they can easily adapt it to do exactly
                                                  what they require to get their research done.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="intr_which-operating-system-is-best">
                                        <title>Which operating system is best?</title>
                                        <para>Our consumer culture puts huge stress on having "the best". Usually this means wearing some fashionable
                                                  brand of jeans, or driving a fancy car. Obviously this is a very superficial measurement, and we
                                                  have to look deeper when trying to compare operating systems.</para>
                                        <para>It's important to remember that computer science is relatively young. I don't think that any operating
                                                  system has been in continuous use for longer than a single human lifespan. At the dawn of the
                                                  computer age, there was a great explosion of diversity, like in the Cambrian period in prehistory,
                                                  when different designs and architectures proliferated. This was succeed by a period of
                                                  consolidation, with the result that today (even though the details "under the hood" may be very
                                                  different) a great deal of consensus has emerged about the types of services an operating system
                                                  should provide. <footnote>
                                                            <para>This consensus is reflected in <emphasis>standards</emphasis>, such as the <ulink
                                                                           url="http://www.pasc.org/#POSIX"> Portable Operating System
                                                                      Interface</ulink> ( <acronym>POSIX</acronym>).</para>
                                                  </footnote></para>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                                  <imageobject>
                                                            <imagedata fileref="../images/operating-joke.png"/>
                                                  </imageobject>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                        <para>At the moment, the operating systems you're likely to encounter on desktops are to some extent
                                                  interchangeable. Linux, Macintosh OS X and Windows all implement <acronym>POSIX</acronym> to some
                                                  degree. Software that was written to make use portable use of the operating system's services may be
                                                  compiled to run on all of them.</para>
                                        <para>These operating systems can all do the same jobs, and you may develop skills that apply to other
                                                  operating systems on any of them. Therefor there is no quick, objective answer to the question as
                                                  which one is "best". You have to forget that one, and ask a better question: "Which operating system
                                                  is best <emphasis>for me</emphasis>?"</para>
                                        <para>Well, of course that depends on who you are and what you need it for. If you're interested in
                                                  &productname;s then you probably don't have lots and lots of money, and you're probably
                                                  interested in learning: learning about computers, yes, but also education in general. When answering
                                                  this question for yourself, here are two things to keep in mind:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <formalpara>
                                                                      <title>How does it impact the world I live in?</title>
                                                                      <para>The software you choose can influence many aspects of your life. For
                                                                           example, you need to ask: "Who controls the technology?" If you teach
                                                                           yourself to use a product that belongs to some company, you'd better
                                                                           hope that they don't go out of business.</para>
                                                            </formalpara>
                                                            <para>Governments are also starting to use computers for tasks such as counting votes.
                                                                      During the previous two elections in America, there was great controversy about
                                                                      the results turned in by Diebold's vote counting machines. Diebold controls the
                                                                      software, and expect voters to take the trustworthiness of their software on
                                                                      faith. For matters such as this, democracies in the digital age must use open
                                                                      source software.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <formalpara>
                                                                      <title>Current technical merit is only one measure</title>
                                                                      <para>Even if something is imperfect now, if you can get at it, you can make it
                                                                           better and learn in the process.</para>
                                                            </formalpara>
                                                            <para>For example, the open source program called the <application>GIMP</application> (the
                                                                      GNU Image Manipulation Program) goes head-to-head with Adobe
                                                                           <application>Photoshop</application>. At the moment, Photoshop still
                                                                      comes out pretty far ahead, but it has been under continuous development for a
                                                                      decade or more. Does this mean that aspiring designers should turn their back on
                                                                      the GIMP? If they do, they lose the things that the GIMP already gives them
                                                                      which Photoshop doesn't, such as the ability to write extensions in a variety of
                                                                      high-level programming languages, and to build on the contributions of the
                                                                      entire community of users.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section id="intr_what-is-a-distribution">
                              <title>What is a distribution?</title>
                              <para>In the following text, you'll read about a number of different <emphasis>distributions</emphasis>, e.g. Debian,
                                        K12LTSP and RedHat Fedora. This is a term that emerged from the open source way of gathering and organising
                                        software for sharing: a coherent, well-maintained, up-to-date collection of software (especially on the scale
                                        of an operating system) is called a <emphasis>distribution</emphasis>.</para>
                              <para>As you saw above, Linux is the source code of an operating system being written by hundreds of volunteers who
                                        pursue their own goals and interests. It uses tools from other projects, such as the GNU project, and is used
                                        on a very wide range of machines, for widely varying goals. From this, you may imagine that it is a hugely
                                        complex system, and you'd be right. Assembling just the subset of code that is relevant to you, and compiling
                                        it to run optimally on the hardware that you happen to have, is a major undertaking requiring deep skill and
                                        experience. Keeping your system up to date with changes in disparate parts of the whole is a major undertaking
                                        in itself.</para>
                              <para>In order to have a manageable system, well-understood and reasonably easy to customise and keep up to date, groups
                                        of users began to band together to collect just the right combinations of software, and to coordinate this
                                        job. Some people built their business around the process of gathering, labelling, testing, documenting and
                                        marketing free software, for example RedHat and SuSE. Some communities assemble distributions that conform to
                                        their ideals; Debian, for example, operates in accordance with a <ulink
                                                  url="http://www.debian.org/social_contract"> Social Contract</ulink> which maintains the same
                                        principles of good husbandry and mutual cooperation that prompted Richard Stallman to found the Free Software
                                        Foundation.</para>
                              <para>&productname;s and Wizzy actually make use of no less than <emphasis>four</emphasis> related distributions. <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The classroom server runs a modified K12LTSP distribution, and</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>the Wizzy server is based on Whitebox Linux.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>K12LTSP, in turn, is based on RedHat Fedora;</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>and Whitebox Linux is based on RedHat Enterprise.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist> In part, the reasons for the variation are historical: the Wizzy solution was developed
                                        independently of the &productname; project.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section id="intr_where-it-all-began">
                              <title>Where it all began</title>
                              <section id="intr_academic-computer-science-background">
                                        <title>Academic computer science background</title>
                                        <para>The idea of free software, with source code that could be shared by everyone, started in academia. In
                                                  America, it was Richard Stallman at MIT, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, who started the
                                                  ball rolling, but the person who accidentally turned it into an avalanche was Linus Torvalds, a
                                                  Finnish university student.</para>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                                  <imageobject>
                                                            <imagedata fileref="../images/stallman.png"/>
                                                  </imageobject>
                                                  <caption>Richard Stallman</caption>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                        <para>At MIT, Stallman had been part of a community of programmers that came to an end when their work was
                                                  commercialised and access to the source code was restricted. To Stallman, this felt like having the
                                                  air he needed to breathe cut off. Because Stallman believed strongly that programmers should be able
                                                  to help one another by sharing their source code, he set out to write a complete free operating
                                                  system. He began systematically, though, first setting out to write all the supporting tools that an
                                                  operating system requires to work. This is a mammoth task, and in fact they're still busy refining
                                                  better and better tools.</para>
                                        <para>Linus Torvalds, in Helsinki, wasn't burdened with any such a sense of responsibility or thoroughness. He
                                                  just wanted to make the most of the PC he had at home, which had an Intel 80386
                                                  <acronym>CPU</acronym>. The 80386 contained a memory management unit, which was big news at the
                                                  time. The operating systems he had at his disposal didn't take advantage of this and he dearly
                                                  wanted to use it, and so he started to write his <emphasis>own</emphasis> operating system. To do
                                                  this, he used many of the tools created by the GNU project. After months and months of steady work,
                                                  he released a very early version of the kernel that became known as Linux to the internet. To his
                                                  surprise, other people started sending him fixes and improvements for his kernel, and eventually he
                                                  found himself managing and coordinating a global community of programmers. All of them were using
                                                  and improving Linux, and building on each others' work.</para>
                                        <mediaobject>
                                                  <imageobject>
                                                            <imagedata fileref="../images/linus.png"/>
                                                  </imageobject>
                                                  <caption>Linus Torvalds</caption>
                                        </mediaobject>
                                        <para>In a sense, the free software community that Stallman had known at MIT had risen anew, on a global
                                                  scale. Their rallying point was a system made up of the Linux kernel, and the GNU development
                                                  environment.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="intr_open-source-software">
                                        <title>Open Source Software</title>
                                        <para>The first one to think of a name for the kind of software that could be shared without restrictions on
                                                  how you could use it was Richard Stallman. He called it Free Software, because he wanted to
                                                  emphasise the freedoms that he valued highly enough to dedicate his life to writing a free operating
                                                  system.</para>
                                        <para>The <ulink url="http://www.fsf.org"> Free Software Foundation</ulink> supports the freedoms of speech,
                                                  press, and association on the internet, the right to use encryption software for private
                                                  communication, and the right to write software unimpeded by private monopolies. Stallman formulated
                                                  a license, the <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"> GNU Public License</ulink>, which
                                                  uses the mechanism of copyright to protect these freedoms, and to add the responsibility of passing
                                                  them on to other users of the software.</para>
                                        <para>When Linux started to be noticed by business, and when it began to be marketed as a serious IT platform,
                                                  this emphasis on freedom made some people uncomfortable. The argument was that people don't run
                                                  their businesses in order to advance someone's freedom of speech --- they run their business to make
                                                  money!</para>
                                        <para>Instead of emphasising the <emphasis>freedom</emphasis> aspects so dear to Stallman's heart, more
                                                  emphasis was placed on the fact that everyone had access to the source code of Linux. The programmer
                                                  and writer Eric Raymond wrote some <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/">
                                                            influential papers</ulink> in which he argued that the Linux style of community
                                                  development produced <emphasis>better software</emphasis> than the proprietary alternative. The
                                                  choice for open source software could be made on a purely pragmatic basis. The critical factor, in
                                                  his view, was the availability of the source code, and therefor he coined the term <emphasis>Open
                                                            Source</emphasis> to describe this kind of software.</para>
                                        <para>The contrast may be summed up in the sentence: "Open source is a development methodology; free software
                                                  is a social movement." <ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/free-software-for-freedom.html">
                                                            <acronym>FSF</acronym>
                                                  </ulink></para>
                                        <para>Neither one of these approaches encompass the whole truth, they simply emphasise different aspects of a
                                                  rich sphere of human endeavour. The pragmatic approach taken by &productname;s in the selection
                                                  of software for inclusion leans more toward the open source side of the debate, but the Shuttleworth
                                                  Foundation's goal of "social innovation" is in line with the <acronym>FSF</acronym> philosophy.</para>
                                        <para>Various other streams exists. The BSD license of the <ulink url="http://www.freebsd.org">
                                                  FreeBSD</ulink> project, for example, does not specify the responsibilities of the GPL, and allows
                                                  code under the BSD license to be incorporated into proprietary software. For many years, for
                                                  example, the Windows <acronym>TCP/IP</acronym> stack <!-- (see <xref linkend="intr_tcp-ip"/>) -->
                                                  was based on BSD code right up to the period of <application>Windows 2000</application>--- perhaps
                                                  it still is?</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="intr_open-source-culture">
                                        <title>Open Source Culture</title>
                                        <para>As the open source culture matured, the principles of mutual education, self-sufficiency and sharing
                                                  were applied to many things besides software. One of the first projects to bring the wider world of
                                                  culture into the open source community was <ulink url="http://www.gutenberg.org/"> Project
                                                  Gutenberg</ulink>, a project to make available as many as possible public domain and freely
                                                  redistributable texts at no cost. Due to recent changes in American legislation (which enables
                                                  copyright holders to keep works out of the public domain forever), this essentially means works
                                                  created before 1923. At the moment, there are more than 13,000 books <ulink
                                                            url="http://www.gutenberg.org/catalog/"> available for download</ulink>.</para>
                                        <para>Another open source project is the <ulink url="http://www.wikipedia.org/"> Wikipedia</ulink>, an online
                                                  encyclopedia read and edited entirely by volunteers. The English edition, started in 2001, already
                                                  has almost half a million articles. If your &productname; includes a Wizzy internet server, the
                                                  entire Wikipedia can be made available on the &productname; network.</para>
                                        <para>
                                                  <ulink url="http://www.lessig.org/"> Larry Lessig</ulink>, a law professor at Stanford, noticed the
                                                  need to apply the open source principles of collaboration and sharing in other domains besides
                                                  software, and set about crafting a flexible set of licenses that could be used to bring music,
                                                  books, movies and educational material into the open source world. Since his project has as a goal
                                                  the re-establishment of a <emphasis>commons</emphasis>, a area for the use of the community as a
                                                  whole, to replace the endangered public domain, these licenses are called the <ulink
                                                            url="http://creativecommons.org/"> Creative Commons</ulink> licenses.</para>
                                        <section id="intr_why-do-people-do-this">
                                                  <title>Why do people do this?</title>
                                                  <para>There are many reasons, but I'll mention only one. Far more expensive than the recording of a
                                                            song, or the writing of a book, is the task of promoting, printing and distributing it.
                                                            Unless this task can be handed over to everyone who reads or listens, only large media
                                                            companies are able to afford this cost. A creative commons license allows authors to
                                                            publish work that the media companies are not interested in.</para>
                                        </section>
                              </section>
                              <section id="intr_open-source-in-education">
                                        <title>Open Source in education</title>
                                        <para>Free Software can be a valuable resource in education, and can also promote the values of the GNU
                                                  project, namely freedom and cooperation, in schools.</para>
                                        <para>There are general reasons why all computer users should insist on free software. <footnote>
                                                            <para>Source for the following paragraphs: <ulink
                                                                           url="http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/schools.html">
                                                                           http://www.fsf.org/philosophy/schools.html</ulink></para>
                                                  </footnote> It gives users the freedom to control their own computers --- with proprietary software,
                                                  the computer does what the software owner wants it to do, not what you want it to do. Free software
                                                  also gives users the freedom to cooperate with each other, to lead an upright life. These reasons
                                                  apply to schools as they do to everyone.</para>
                                        <para>But there are special reasons that apply to schools.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>First, free software saves money. Even in the richest countries, schools are short
                                                                      of money. Free software gives schools, like other users, the freedom to copy and
                                                                      redistribute the software, so the school system can make copies for all the
                                                                      computers they have. This is essential to help close the digital divide.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Secondly, schools should help learners to build a strong society after they leave
                                                                      school. They should promote the use of free software just as they promote
                                                                      recycling and protecting your environment. If schools teach learners about free
                                                                      software, then they will use free software after they leave school. This will
                                                                      help communities to be more self-reliant, and will make them less dependent on
                                                                      big corporations who repatriate their profits to other countries.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Thirdly, free software permits learners to find out how software really works. They
                                                                      can go and look at the source code to find out how the operations they use were
                                                                      implemented, and experiment by changing it.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                        <para>Proprietary software rejects their thirst for knowledge: it says, "The knowledge you want is a secret
                                                  --- learning is forbidden!" Free software encourages everyone to learn. The free software community
                                                  rejects the "priesthood of technology", which keeps the general public in ignorance of how
                                                  technology works; we encourage students of any age and situation to read the source code and learn
                                                  as much as they want to know. Schools that use free software will enable gifted programming students
                                                  to advance.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section id="intr_resources">
                                        <title>Resources</title>
                                        <para>Here are pointers to a few of the organisations and projects that work to further the use of free
                                                  software in education:</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The <ulink url="http://www.nl.debian.org/devel/debian-jr/"> Debian Jr.
                                                                      Project</ulink> is a custom Debian distribution. It aims to make Debian an
                                                                           <acronym>OS</acronym> that children will want to use, by studying the
                                                                      needs expressed by the children themselves. Their initial focus is on children
                                                                      up to age 8. Once this goal has been accomplished, their next target age range
                                                                      is 7 to 12.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                      <ulink url="http://www.tux4kids.com/"> Tux4Kids</ulink> provides some great
                                                                      software packages for Debian Jr.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                      <ulink url="http://wiki.debian.net/?DebianEdu"> DebianEdu</ulink> is about
                                                                      improving Debian to make it the best distribution for educational use.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Because they believe that free and equal access to information technology is
                                                                      important in modern society, the <ulink url="http://www.ofset.org/">
                                                                           Organisation for Free Software in Education and Teaching</ulink> is
                                                                      actively promoting and developing free software for schools.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>
                                                                      <ulink url="http://www.schoolforge.net/"> SchoolForge</ulink> is an umbrella
                                                                      organisation or a communication channel for different groupings with the mutual
                                                                      goal to advance open resources at school.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>The <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/osie"> Open Source in Education
                                                                           Project</ulink> (OSiE) supports and advocates the use of GNU/Linux
                                                                      systems in the UK.</para>
                                                            <para>This is just one example of a local project. Others exist in <ulink
                                                                           url="http://fsub.schule.de/"> Germany</ulink>, <ulink
                                                                           url="http://www.linuxdidattica.org/"> Italy</ulink>, <ulink
                                                                           url="http://www.laka.lv/"> Latvia</ulink>, <ulink
                                                                           url="http://www.gleducar.org.ar/"> Argentina</ulink>, and many other
                                                                      countries across the globe.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                    </section>
          </section>
</chapter>
