<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[ 
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../common/global.ent">
 %globalents; 
 <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
 ]>
<chapter>

                    <title>Training Module</title>
                    
                    <abstract>&abstract-training;</abstract>

          <section id="trn_volunteer">
                    <title>Volunteer Training</title>
                    <section id="trn_courses">
                              <title>Course structure</title>
                              <para>The training of &productname; volunteers consists of levels or modules that take a beginning novice and,
                                        through learning and experience, create a &productname; expert. Each module, from 'Boot camp' to
                                        'Reservists', has a specific training course attached. These course give a comprehensive overview of the
                                        features and functionality of Linux, preparing the volunteer for certification of these skills. In-depth
                                        detail is provided for key concepts. Many Linux concepts and utilities are identical regardless of the
                                        specific distribution of Linux that is being used. The nature of Linux and Open source software is such that
                                        changes to source code and changes to functionality of any given component are happening continually. However,
                                        the underlying concepts of Linux capabilities and functionality remain consistent throughout distribution,
                                        kernel and software changes.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Introduction to Linux – Fundamentals</title>
                                        <para>This course provides a 3 day introduction and in-depth explanation of the concepts and principles that
                                                  are necessary to install a Linux system and navigate the command-line and GUI environments. It is
                                                  specifically aimed at Linux novices and people making the transition to Linux. Focus is also given
                                                  to the history of Linux and open source software.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Linux System Administration</title>
                                        <para>This 4 day course will provide participants with a foundation in the concepts and principles that are
                                                  necessary to administer a Linux system. The scope of an administrator's tasks may be very broad.
                                                  Structure and function of the Linux kernel, key administrative topics of managing software packages,
                                                  processes, disk space, backups and users as well as scheduling tasks and system logs are covered in
                                                  this course.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Advanced Workshops</title>
                                        <para>This will be the dynamic course in the offering. If a volunteer finishes both the beginners and
                                                  intermediate courses, they are free to attend as many of these courses as they like, provided they
                                                  meet the requirements set out in the training incentive scheme (see <xref
                                                            linkend="trn_incentive_process"/>. This course will take the form of a 1 day workshop,
                                                  covering advanced Linux services and Open Source topics. This workshop will be run monthly by
                                                  volunteer trainers, once enough volunteers have completed the first two courses.</para>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Facilitator workshops</title>
                                        <para>A hands-on workshop covering all the technical principles and configuration aspects regarding the
                                                  running and maintenance of a &productname; lab. Example lesson plans for introducing learners to
                                                  the &productname; will also be provided and expanded on. This course will be run on a per
                                                  cluster basis and will be exclusive to the computer committee from each cluster school, as well as
                                                  the lab facilitator or volunteers offering free support to the cluster. Eventually, this training
                                                  will be handled by the veteran volunteers.</para>
                              </section>
                    </section>
          </section>
          <section id="trn_incentive_process">
                    <title>The Incentives Process</title>
                    <para>The main incentive offered by the Foundation, to it's volunteers, is GNU/Linux training. In order to be trained on GNU/Linux
                              and it's varying levels of complexity, the volunteer must pass through the following modules, satisfying all the
                              associated requirements. Please refer to the following diagram for a better understanding of the process.</para>
                    <figure>
                              <title>Training Modules Process</title>
                              <mediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                                  <imagedata fileref="../images/Volunteer_Training_Process.png"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                              </mediaobject>
                    </figure>
                    <procedure>
                              <step>
                                        <para>Joe would start out by helping install a&productname;. He would learn how to network a computer room
                                                  and know the basics behind cabling.</para>
                              </step>
                              <step>
                                        <para>At the next &productname; installation, Joe will learn how to prepare the workstation computer and
                                                  discover how the network card, in the computer, accesses the server.</para>
                              </step>
                              <step>
                                        <para>After those two practical sessions, Joe will register for the module’s course. If he’s a beginner, the
                                                  first course will be Linux Fundamentals. Joe will have the choice of doing this 3 day course either
                                                  full-time or part-time.</para>
                              </step>
                              <step>
                                        <para>Once Joe has finished the module’s course, he will be expected to help install one more
                                                  &productname; in order to move on to the next module and receive more advanced training.</para>
                              </step>
                    </procedure>
          </section>
          <section>
                    <title>Training Modules</title>
                    <section>
                              <title>Module 1 - “Boot camp”</title>
                              <para>Candidates will have to actively participate in 2 (two) &productname; installations, prior to the
                                        "Introduction to Linux - Fundamentals" course, and 1 (one) installation thereafter. These activities will be
                                        run in succession.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 1 - “Scrubs”</title>
                                        <para>The volunteer will be assigned to do the cabling in a &productname;. Instructions will be provided
                                                  by the lab representative (see assessment) or module 2 volunteer, for the layout of the cabling, as
                                                  well as the physical detail of the cable, connectors and crimping tool. Worksheets will be provided
                                                  with all the theory required for advancement. At any given stage the participants will be asked to
                                                  demonstrate the process to new volunteers or to the lab representative (see assessment).</para>
                                        <para>Only once the volunteer has fully participated in this activity, and can demonstrate his/her new skill,
                                                  will they be able to move to the next level in the next &productname; installation. </para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level 1 - Skills objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Know the make-up of cat5 cabling.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Know the differences between popular network topologies. (Star, bus, etc.)</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Know how to crimp network points.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Learn how to diagnose and troubleshoot connectivity issues.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 2 - “Newts”</title>
                                        <para>At this level, the volunteer will be responsible for the set-up and operation of the thin-client
                                                  terminals. Instructions will be provided on a worksheet, with additional verbal instruction from the
                                                  lab representative (see assessment). Participants will learn about the requirements for thin-client
                                                  computing as well as the theory of operation. Once again, volunteers will be asked to demonstrate
                                                  their activity to new volunteers or to the lab representative (see assessment).</para>
                                        <para>When the lab has been completed and the accepted level of skill has been displayed, he/she be able to
                                                  advance to level 3 in the next &productname;.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level 2 – Skills objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Know how to insert a network card into a computer.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Understand how the boot-prom works and how it is enabled.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Troubleshoot and diagnose network card and boot-prom problems.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Learn how to use the computer's BIOS options.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 3 - “Newbies”</title>
                                        <para>Level 3 will be the “Introduction to Linux – Fundamentals” course – the first incentive. A maximum of 30
                                                  people can be accommodated at a time. Volunteers who were left behind in previous module1 activities
                                                  and have finished the required pre-training requirements may also enrol for this training course. If
                                                  demand requires, the course will be run when needed to avoid any bottlenecks in the process. Refer
                                                  to the appropriate section in the “Course structure” for the overview.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level3 – Skills objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>History of Linux and open source software.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Linux system installation.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Navigating the command line.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Using the “vi” text editor.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>File system and directory structures.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 4 - “Gnats”</title>
                                        <para>After receiving the training in level 3, volunteers will be required to set-up a &productname;
                                                  server. They will be exposed to the “real-world” challenge of deciding on hard disk partitioning
                                                  schemes, integrating the &productname; with existing network structures and services as well as
                                                  troubleshooting core &productname; configuration. Instruction will be provided by the lab
                                                  representative (see assessment) and participants will receive documentation on the technical aspects
                                                  of the &productname; theory of operation. </para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level 4 - Skills objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Installation and configuration of a Linux server.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Configuration of thin-client settings.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Network and DHCP configuration.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>User and group administration as well as any environmental configuration (network
                                                                      integration etc.).</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                              <title>Module 2 - “In-service training”</title>
                              <para>The module 2 volunteers will be responsible for co-ordinating the practical activities (&productname;
                                        activities) of the next batch of module 1 volunteers. Their “Basic Training” skills will be tested by teaching
                                        the new module 1 volunteers how to complete each practical level of the 1st module. This group will, for
                                        example, teach the new volunteers how to cable a lab and crimp network points, etcetera.</para>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 1 - “Squire”</title>
                                        <para>The volunteer will have up to four module1 “Scrubs” assigned to him/her. General instructions will be
                                                  provided by the lab representative. It is up to the module 2 volunteers to make sure that his/her
                                                  “Scrubs” can complete all the tasks and meet the module 1 – level 1 skills objectives. Once the lab
                                                  representative is happy that the “Squire's” have passed on their knowledge to the “Scrubs”, and the
                                                  “Scrubs” can demonstrate their new skills to the lab representative, will the “Squires” be allowed
                                                  to advance.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level 1 – Skills Objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Communication skills.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Basic team leadership.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Knowledge retention and recall.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Skills evaluation.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 2 - “Delagator”</title>
                                        <para>Again, the volunteer will have one to four module1 “Newts” assigned to him/her. General instructions
                                                  will be provided by the lab representative. It is up to the module 2 volunteers to make sure that
                                                  his/her “Newts” can complete all the tasks and meet the module 1 – level 2 skills objectives. Only
                                                  once the lab representative is happy that the “Delagators” have passed on their knowledge to the
                                                  “Newts”, and the “Newts” can demonstrate their new skills to the lab representative, will the
                                                  “Delagators” be allowed to advance.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level 2 – Skills objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Team leadership or one on one interaction.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Technical communication.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 3 - “Initiates”</title>
                                        <para>Level 3 will be the “Linux System Administration” course. A maximum of 30 people can be accommodated at
                                                  a time. Volunteers who were left behind in previous module2 activities and have finished the
                                                  required pre-training requirements may also enrol for this training course. If demand requires, the
                                                  course will be run when needed to avoid any bottlenecks in the process. Refer to the appropriate
                                                  section in the “Course structure” for the overview.</para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                                  <title>Level 3 – Skills objectives:</title>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Understanding the Linux Kernel.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>System backups.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>File system Hierarchy Standard.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>Package management and</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                                  <listitem>
                                                            <para>System log files.</para>
                                                  </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                              </section>
                              <section>
                                        <title>Level 4 - “Top Dogs”</title>
                                        <para>Only two volunteers will be selected to fulfill the role of training module1 “Gnats” to set up a
                                                  &productname; server. This is a specialized activity that requires a good understanding of how a
                                                  &productname; works. Unfortunately, an excessive number of volunteers participating in this
                                                  activity will not benefit anyone. The two “Top Dogs” will be selected from the level 3 system
                                                  administration course and selection will be based on individual performance during the the training.
                                                  Instruction will be provided by the lab representative and participants will receive documentation
                                                  on the technical aspects of the &productname; theory of operation. </para>
                                        <para>The rest of the module 2 volunteers can proceed on to the next module once they have received the
                                                  &productname; theory of operation document.</para>
                              </section>
                    </section>
                    <section id="reservists">
                              <title>Module 3 - “Reservists”</title>
                              <para>The process of setting up a &productname; doesn't change much. The cabling, thin-clients and server still need
                                        to be set-up and configured. In this stage the volunteer may be expected to supervise any of the Module1 and 2
                                        activities - even then only a finite number of new experiences can be gained at each &productname;.
                                        Module3 volunteers will be required to participate in the set-up of at least 1(one) &productname; in order
                                        to proceed to the next training class, “Advanced Workshops”. That way, once everything is known about setting
                                        up a &productname;, volunteers will not get bored with the activities but instead see them as a means to
                                        “pay” for GNU/Linux training. The Shuttleworth &productname; program will therefore be successful if
                                        volunteers have something tangible to attain – certifiable skills (see “Training”). Also, as the process of
                                        setting up &productname;s becomes more easy for the majority of volunteers, the Foundation can step back
                                        and merely facilitate the process.</para>
                              <para>During this phase, additional incentives may be provided at the Foundation's discretion. Examples include, but are
                                        not limited to: t-shirts, Linux copies and food at events.</para>
                    </section>
                    <section>
                              <title>Public recognition</title>
                              <para>Setting up an &productname; is great. Receiving public acknowledgement is even better! Once a volunteer has
                                        completed all the GNU/Linux courses and reached module 3, he/she will have the facility to manage an on-line
                                        “portfolio”.</para>
                              <para>The Foundation will showcase it's successful volunteers by giving them a web page containing details of their
                                        activity within the Shuttleworth &productname; project. The page will display a picture of the volunteer
                                        and have all their relevant statistics, how many labs they participated in, peer statements, what training
                                        they received etc. This could be used as an employment tool for the unemployed volunteer or as a bragging
                                        piece for the employed section.</para>
                    </section>
          </section>
</chapter>
