<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
	"http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[ 
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../common/global.ent">
%globalents; 
]>-->
<sect1 id="conventions">
    <title>Conventions</title>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">The following admonitions will be found throughout the book:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <note>
        <para>A note presents interesting, sometimes technical, pieces of information related to the
            surrounding discussion.</para>
    </note>
    <tip>
        <para>A tip offers advice or an easier way of doing something.</para>
    </tip>
    <caution>
        <para>A caution advises you of potential problems and helps you to steer clear thereof.</para>
    </caution>
    <warning>
        <para>A warning advises you of a hazard condition that may be created in a given scenario.</para>
    </warning>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Cross reference conventions for print will be shown as follows:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Internal references will look like this: <xref linkend="introduction"/>. The
                numeral contained by square braces is the [page number].</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>External reference, say to a Web Site, will look like <ulink
            	url="http://www.inwords.co.za">this</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
        <para>PDF, HTML or XHTML versions of this document will use hyper-links to denote cross-references.</para>
    </note>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Type conventions will be shown as follows:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>File names or paths to directories will be shown in <filename>monospace</filename> type.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Commands that you type at a prompt will be shown in <command> bold</command> type.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Options that you click, select or choose in the user interface will be shown in
                <filename>monospace</filename> type.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>When variables, parameters, SGML tags, etc. are contained within a paragraph of
                text, they will be shown in <command>monospaced</command> type. Otherwise they will
                use the normal type.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Menu selections, mouse actions, and keyboard short-cuts:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>A sequence of menu selections will be shown as follows:<menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>
                        <accel>F</accel>ile</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>
                        <accel>O</accel>pen</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Mouse actions shall assume a right-handed mouse configuration. The terms
                &quot;<mousebutton>click</mousebutton>&quot; and
                &quot;<mousebutton>double-click</mousebutton>&quot; refers to using the
                left-hand mouse button. The term
                &quot;<mousebutton>right-click</mousebutton>&quot; refers to using the
                right-hand button.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Keyboard short-cut combinations will be shown as follows: <keycombo>
                    <keysym>Ctrl+N</keysym>
                </keycombo>. Where the convention for &quot;Control&quot;,
                &quot;Shift&quot;, and &quot;Alternate&quot; keys will be
                <keysym>Ctrl</keysym>, <keysym>Shift</keysym>, <keysym>Alt</keysym>, respectively,
                and shall mean to hold down the first key while pressing the second key.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Code conventions:</emphasis>
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Code and mark-up samples will be formatted in a grey block.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Sometimes lines of code or mark-up examples will be longer than the page width. To
                avoid their running off the page, the slash character &quot;\&quot; is used
                to denote a soft line break. This means that the line of code is in reality meant to
                be on one line, but for print formatting it has been broken into two lines.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect1>
