<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[ 
<!ENTITY % globalents SYSTEM "../common/global.ent">
 %globalents; 
 <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
 ]>
<appendix id="apdx_awaress_questionnaire">
	<title>School Awareness Questionnaire</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>The Shuttleworth Foundation is committed to the improvement of education, with a specific focus on mathematics, science, entrepreneurship
			and technology, as well as the promotion of open source software in South Africa. As a propagator of `social innovation', the main objective
			of the Shuttleworth Foundation is to invest in projects that provide innovative solutions to educational challenges in order to unlock the
			creative and intellectual potential of the South African youth, allowing them to live the dream that `anything is possible'. </para>
		<para>To further encourage the uptake of technology in South Africa, the Shuttleworth Foundation supports the use of open source software. The
			Shuttleworth Foundation strongly believes that open source software should be the preferred choice of software for schooling in South Africa.
			Open source software provides users with freedoms not obtainable from proprietary software, this includes the freedom to obtain, use, modify
			and distribute the software. The Shuttleworth Foundation believes that the use of open source software will provide effective and economical
			access to information and communication technology.</para>
		<para>In 2002 the Foundation started to actively promote the use open source software as a computer lab solution for schools. The Foundation
			funded several projects to establish open source based computer labs in schools, as well as an internally initiating a pilot to prove the
			effectiveness of open source software as a school computing solution. The Foundation also initiated a project to facilitate the involvement
			of volunteers in refurbishing computers and establishing Shuttleworth tuXlabs.</para>
		<para>Based on the success of the pilot and volunteer project, the Foundation extended the pilot and established a program with the ambitious
			ideal of establishing a further 80 Shuttleworth tuXlabs in the Western Cape over the next two years.</para>
		<para>The Foundation is requesting that schools fill in this questionnaire in order for them to ascertain the requirements of schools for
			computer technology implementations. The questionnaire covers computer use and management, technology and open source knowledge and
			recognition of the foundation within schools. This data will allow us to identify areas where our focus and resources may be required to
			assist with ICT in Education. We appreciate your support.</para>
		<para>If you would like assistance with the questionnaire or require any further information about this research, please contact</para>
		<para>Hilton Theunissen</para>
		<para>Open Source Project Manager</para>
		<para>E-mail: hilton@shuttleworthfoundation.org</para>
		<para>Url: www.shuttleworthfoundation.org</para>
		<para>Tel: 021 970 1212</para>
		<para>Fax: 021 970 1213</para>
		<para>
			<emphasis role="bold">Please complete and return questionnaire below to : </emphasis>
		</para>
		<para>Casey-Lea Olson</para>
		<para>Open Source Project Administrator</para>
		<para>Tel: 021 970 1232</para>
		<para>Fax: 021 970 1233</para>
		<para>E-mail: casey@shuttleworthfoundation.org</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Questionnaire</title>
		<table>
			<title>Participant info:</title>
			<tgroup cols="2" align="left">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>School name</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Address</entry>
						<entry morerows="1"/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry/>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Tel. no</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Fax. no</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>E-mail</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Website</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Principal</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Secretary</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Computer Co-ordinator</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>No. of staff</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>No. of Learners</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>No. of Governing Body Members</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<table>
			<title>Computers in your school:</title>
			<tgroup cols="2" align="left">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>How many computers are used in the school?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Where are the computers used:</entry>
						<entry morerows="3"/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Admin Block: No. of computers:</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Staff room : No. of computers:</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Computer Lab: No of computers:</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Are the computers networked?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Does the school have a computer committee?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>How many members does the committee consist of?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Who are the members?</entry>
						<entry morerows="1"/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry/>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Do the learners pay a fee for participation?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Is the focus computer literacy or curriculum delivery?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Does the school have a teacher who facilitates the classes and does he/she have any formal computer training.</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Who is responsible for daily management of the lab?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Who was responsible for cost of :</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>1. security of the lab</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>2. furniture in the lab</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>3. electrical plugs installation</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>4. computers in the lab</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>When did the school acquire the computers in the lab?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>How was the equipment obtained?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>What speed are the majority computers? e.g. Pentium 1,2,3 or higher </entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Did the school contract a service provider for installation and setup? </entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>If so, who</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Did any staff members participate in setting up the lab?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Who is responsible for software support?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Who is responsible for hardware maintenance?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>What operating and office application software is being used?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Did the school pay for this software?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>If No, how did you get the software?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Are you using educational software? If so, what?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Did the staff get literacy and technical training?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Was there any form of certification?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Is the school staff utilising this lab?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Does the school have Internet access in the lab?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Who pays for the connectivity?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>What is the monthly cost?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<table>
			<title>Open source:</title>
			<tgroup cols="2" align="left">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Has the school heard of Open source software before?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>What does the school understand about the term?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Where did the school learn about Open source? </entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Has any staff member attended a tuXlab installation?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>What Open Source software does the school know or use ?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>How is the Open source software being used?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Has the school heard about the Shuttleworth tuXlabs program?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Would the school like to be included in our tuXlab program?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Where did you hear about them?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Has the school heard of our volunteer program?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry> If so, where?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<table>
			<title>The Shuttleworth Foundation</title>
			<tgroup cols="2" align="left">
				<colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
				<colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Has the school heard about the Shuttleworth Foundation?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Where did the school hear about the foundation?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>What does the Foundation do?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Does the school know of any of our projects?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Has school visited our website before?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Has the school seen any of our newsletters?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Has the school submitted a proposal previously to the Foundation?</entry>
						<entry/>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>Other comments:</para>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para/>
		<para>Thank you for taking the time to fill out this form as accurately as possible. We greatly appreciate your assistance.</para>
		<para>Confidential Disclosure:</para>
		<para>We hereby confirm that the school details and information completed will not be made available to anybody outside the Foundation unless
			approved by the school by means of letter. The Foundation will provide the school with copy of results and the original will be stored at the
			Foundation's offices.</para>
	</section>
</appendix>
